A Guide to the William Francis Brand Civil War Letters, 1856-1959 (bulk 1857-1866)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout 1861-1867
  - WFB, camp near Liberty Mills, to "Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1862 July 25
    his brother John is still sickly but brother David [Charles David Brand, 1838-1904] has returned from a visit to their grandmother's; Robert Taylor discharged for being over age thirty-five; the regiment finally assigned a chaplain, Edward Payson Walton [?-?], "a very good preacher"; WFB says he "had a wonderful time Saturday hunting for deserters," Frank Taylor arrested but later escaped from his guards Isaac Newton Vines [1834-1913] and George W. Hight [Hite] [?-1897]
  - WFB, Camp M ?, to "Dear Kate," Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1862 August 15
    describes the battle of Cedar Mountain [9 August 1862], wounding of his brothers John W. Brand [1842-1923] and Charles David Brand [1838-1904], both sent to Charlottesville Hospital; he and Samuel B. Fitch [?- 1876; medical discharge November 1861] are no longer intimate as "he has a smooth tongue & seems to be a real ladies man"
  - WFB, Bellmont Hospital, Nelson County, to "Friend Kate," Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1862 August 29
    passing reference to Union General John Pope [1822-1892] and her brother John Armentrout [1832-1863]; criticizes the hospital ("this is a very mean hospital very little accommodations nothing but bread & meat")
  - WFB, Camp Stonewall [near Winchester], to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1862 Sept. 2
    "The enemy have a large Cavalry force in the Valley & our own Cavalry being afraid of them but us to a good deal of trouble"; hard march last night through mud and rain; expresses sympathy over the death of her cousin in battle and "great many deaths in old Augusta since I left—I believe disease cuts off as many as the sword"
  - WFB, Camp Winder, to "Dear Friend," Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1863 Jan. 2
    has safely returned to camp from his furlough; spent a lonely night in Staunton during his return trip; passing reference to a recent victory in Tennessee; the army in the best of spirits; describes camp life and duties; fellow soldier John M. Meek [1832-1896] has returned from furlough; WFB signs this letter "Willie boy"
  - WFB, Camp Winder, Caroline County, Virginia, to "Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1863 Jan. 19
    oysters cost six dollars a gallon here; Company E at sixty men, is the largest in the brigade; troops constructing winter quarters with chimneys and securing good supplies of wood and water; "I have often been near you in my dreams since I last saw you"
  - WFB, Camp Winder, to "Dear Friend," Lexington, w/envelope 1863 Feb. 6
    Is writing at 9:00 p.m.; snow and rain last two weeks and muddy roads; entertainment skills of Captain Marshall Smith Brown [1840-1907] "a good performer and noble singer"; Captain James W. Newton [1838-1896] started home on furlough and Lieutenant John J. Dempster [1835-1918] has joined the officers' mess; thanks her for sending cheese
  - WFB, "At Home," to "Dear Friend," w/envelope "Miss Kate Armentrout/At Home" 1863 April 7
    asks her forgiveness for delaying replies to her letters; has been in poor health since he came home on leave but feeling better; family and local news
  - WFB, "At Home" [Steeles Tavern] to "Dear Friend," w/envelope [this letter originally cris-cross folded] 1863 April 30
    visited George Newton Britton [?-1909] who is in poor health, and his fiancee Lizzie Brown; other family news and local gossip; his brother Tom [Thomas H. Brand, ?-1863] has just reminded him it is noon and time to go to work in the cornfield; concludes with a poem "Thou Shall not, O My Love/Ever hear my voice in rage"; signs himself as "Willie"
  - WFB, "At Home," to "Dear Friend," w/envelope "Miss Kate Armentrout/At Home/G[reenville] A[ugusta] C[ounty] V[irginia]" 1863 May 23
    part of the bone of his big toe removed; has the blues but hopes to see her soon, describes Dr. Hay's operation on his toe, is now on crutches, signs himself as "Willie"
  - WFB, Greenville, to "My Dearest Kate," w/envelope "Miss Kate Armentrout/At Home" 1863 June 6
    his big toe is healing, saw her brother George Armentrout this morning; signs himself as "Willie"
  - WFB, camp near Orange County, Virginia, to "My Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1863 Sept. 16
    Confederate cavalry defeated and drove the enemy toward Rapidan River after a brief skirmish near Culpeper Court House [14 September 1863]; enemy recrossed the Rapidan at Raccoon Ford but was repulsed by General Jubal Early [1816-1894]; with fifty men Company E is the regiment's largest; good preaching in camp by Reverend Mr. Taylor of Staunton before an audience of 5,000 soldiers; declares his love for her: "there is not a beat of my [heart] but beats true to thee O how often I think of the past when you ware by my side: My arms encircling your waist & your sweet lips gently prest to mine then I was so happy"
  - WFB, "On Pickett," to "Dearest Kate," Greenville, w/envelope and detached small piece continuation of his letter 1863 Oct. 11
    enemy watching them from the north side of the Rapidan River; Confederates hope to trade tobacco for coffee with them; her brother "Jake" caused him to blush in camp when he told other soldiers that WFB was writing to his sister [ACA]; the ink he uses to write letters is homemade from pokeroot
  - WFB, Camp near Brandy Station, Virginia, to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1863 Oct. 21
    wishes he could get leave to attend wedding of her cousin and a mutual friend "but alas I had to serve my country first"; troops busily constructing winter camp quarters
  - WFB, Camp Dale, near Brandy Station, to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1863 Nov. 2
    her previous letter delivered to him by her father; suffering from a cold; death of his brother Thomas Brand [?-1863] [at battle of Bealton Station, October 26, 1863, during Bristoe Station Campaign, August- October 1863]
  - WFB, Camp Stonewall Brigade, to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1863 Nov. 24
    because of the bad weather (a cold rain) the President [Jefferson Davis, 1808-1889] canceled his planned review of the troops; rumor that brigade commander General Richard Ewell [1817-1872] is dead [he was wounded at Kelly's Ford, November 7, 1863, Bristoe Station Campaign], George Newton Britton is in next bunk writing a letter to his sister
  - WFB, Camp Kandought(?), to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1864 Jan. 21
    fears she loves another and accuses her of unfaithfulness: "If you should learn to love another man better than me; or that you could enjoy your future happiness better with your first lover [not John P. Lightner; he was dead since 1862] than with poor W [William] I would be heartless not to free you & forgive you... but pray to Almighty God to help you to prove true to whoever you love best"
  - [WFB] to "My own Dear Friend" [letter damaged and incomplete] 1864 Feb. 22
    "You have no idea how glad I was when you Dear letter was handed me"
  - WFB, Essex County, Va. to "My Dear Friend," Dunnsville, [Essex County] Va., w/envelope 1864 March 17
    letter is on yellow stationery and mostly unreadable
  - WFB, "Camp Stonewall Brigade," to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1864 March 24
    describes a snowball fight near Winchester [March 12, 1864], involving 2,000 Confederate troops, involving his brigade [General James Alexander Walker] Walker's Brigade versus [General Robert Emmett Rodes] Rodes' Division: "Thare was none killed on either side but a great many bloody noses"; expresses religious sentiments, faithfulness to her and his goal "to make you happy"
  - WFB, "Camp Randolph," to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1864 April 10
    has spent the afternoon of "this blessed [Sunday] at our little chapel"' expresses love and devotion" "I love you yes passionately & if you think you have ever treated me wrong I forgive thee"
  - WFB, "On Picket near Morton's Ford," to "Dear Friend" 1864 April 23
    hard march this morning; rumor of General James A. Longstreet's [1821-1904] Corps in Madison County; mentions a mutual friend named "Old Charly": "I think of him every day poor fellow; he has had a long stay in Yankee prison; he must be tired & disgusted with Yankee prisons"
  - WFB, Greenville to "Dear Friend," Lexington, w/envelope 1864 May 16
    describes battle of Spotsylvania [May 12, 1864] and his wounded right arm, many Confederates taken prisoner, describes regiment's casualties and prisoners
  - WFB, "At Home," to "My dear K.": asks forgiveness for not visiting her; promises to visit and stay with her at least two days, wishes it could be longer "but it might not look well; his wound has nearly healed 1864 June 3
  - WFB to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1864 June 10?
    letter is on purple stationery and mostly unreadable
  - WFB, Camp Stonewall Brigade [to Amanda C. Armentrout], Greenville, w/envelope 1864 Aug. 19
    returned safely on the 15th; the army is encamped at a fortified position at Fishers Hill near Strasburg; awaiting attack by the enemy; rumors the army will march to Maryland; mentions meeting barefooted Valley girls "awkward in their manners"
  - WFB, Camp Stonewall Brigade, to "Dear Friend," w/envelope addressed to "Miss Kate Armentrout," Greenville" 1864 Sept. 13
    reports and describes the capture of her brother Jacob C. Armentrout [1842-1932], Sergeant Samuel W. Hayes [1829-1888], James W. B. Trotter [?-1864], Samuel E. Lightner [?-1904], and James A. Hutchinson [1844- 1922] and death of Ephraim Y. Strasburg [?-1864] during a skirmish on the 12th [a photocopy of this letter is also present]
  - WFB, "In Line of Battle at Fishers Hill," to "Dear Kate" 1864 Sept. 22
    describes the battle of Fisher's Hill, "we ware badly whipped, death of Major General Robert Emmett Rodes [1829-1864], William Plunkett [1844-1879] wounded, Colonel John Henry Stover Funk [1837-1864] mortally wounded, Captain James W. Newton [1838-1896] seriously wounded in leg, Captain James Bumgardner, Jr. [1835-1917] "killed" [captured]
  - WFB, Brown's Gap [to Amanda C. Armentrout?] w/envelope "Mr. William F. Brand, Lexington, Rockbridge County, Va." yet is postmarked Marion, Alabama(!) 1864 Sept. 25
    continued discussion of the aftermath of defeat at Fishers Hill, loss of artillery and capture of several members of the regiment [John H. Hite [?-1910], Thomas J. Smith [?-?] and William R. Holbert [1836- 1894]; this letter is faint and hard to read
  - WFB, Camp Stonewall Brigade, to "Dear Friend Kate" [letter accidently torn by WFB] 1864 Oct. 2
    skirmish and defeat of Yankee cavalry at Brown's Gap [September 26, 1864; during Sheridan's Shenandoah Valley Campaign]; "Excuse this torn letter"
  - WFB, "Fishers Hill," to "Dearest Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1864 Oct. 15
    says Early [General Jubal Early, 1816-1894] drinks but the "army has not entirely lost confidence in our old leader"; complains of irregular mail service; visited an uncle and his new "young wife"; local and family news
  - WFB, Greenville, to "My Dear Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1864 Oct. 28
    mentions someone as fearful of capture by provost guard; discusses the "hard and bloody" battle of Cedar Creek [19 October 1864] where WFB was wounded in the foot, Confederates routed; is looking forward to visiting "my little bird"
  - WFB, "Camp Ewell," to "My Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1865 Feb. 14
    letter is very faint; cold weather and 15 inches of snow in the Valley; camp news and rumors
  - WFB, "Camp near Petersburg," to "My Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1865 March 22
    discusses rumors of General Joseph E. Johnston [1807-1891] and the battle of Bentonville, North Carolina [March 19-21, 1865]; WFB's camp is only fifty yards away from the enemy, the two forces are sociable and trade newspapers and coffee; "I am certain if this war was left in the hands of the private peace would soon be adjusted"; describes camp life
  - [WFB], Alone Mills [Rockbridge County] to [ACA] 1865 Aug. 11
    General comments; wheat and corn are ready; "This is a beautiful night all nature seems clothes in bridal Splendor"
  - WFB, Alone Mills [Rockbridge County] to "Miss Kate," w/envelope addressed to "Mr. William F. Brand, Alone, Rockbridge Co., Virginia" 1865 Dec. 12
    "The last time I was in your presence you desired to be united in the holy band of marriage in November"; reminds her that she once stated "you never would be willing to marry me until I had some little home of my own... I fear many moons will grow old before I can claim a home of my own" but is willing to get married next fall; "if you will wait until another summer I will give thee my hand with my heart"
  - WFB, "Alone Mills," Rockbridge County, to "Dear Kate" 1865 ?
    plans to visit her next Saturday; "You are always near me in my thoughts Every plan I form or every hope I entertain you are with me"
- WFB Letters to ACA (selected) 1866-1867
  - WFB, "Alone Mills," to "Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1866 Jan. 9
    "You are well aware I once loved you devotedly, yes passionately"
  - WFB, "Poor Creek," to "Dear Kate," w/envelope 1866 April 5
    "I will not deny the charge of swearing occasionally & God knows I am sorry to think this confession but I never shall try to deceive you in the least"; he has just returned from a business trip to Staunton
  - WFB, "Alone Mills," to "My Friend," Greenville, w/envelope 1866 April 22
    "It is due to your goodness womanly virtues & high & honorable nature, to use truth & candor"
  - WFB, "Alone Mills," to [Miss Kate Armentrout], w/envelope 1866 May 24
    doubts about his suitability for marriage; denies rumor that he is in love with "a lady of wealth"; signs himself "your Brother"
  - [WFB], "Alone Mills," to "Dear Kate" 1866 July 21
    "I would like very much to see you; But have thought it best that we should not meet for awhile"
  - [WFB], "Alone [Mills]," to "Dear Friend" 1866 Aug. 9
    "It would have given me much pleasure to have accompanied you to the Pines If for no other reasons; than to show the world we are friends"
  - WFB, "Alone Mills," to "Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1867 Jan. 10
    "I am at a loss what to know what to do this year; I have the offer of a good mill"
  - WFB, "Alone Mills," to "My Dear Wife" [Kate A. Brand], Greenville, w/envelope 1867 Nov. 15
    "I know you are getting anxious to hear from your W. [William] or at least a peep at Kate's face would not be objectionable to the writer thare is none can fill your plase in my affections"; mentions a horse dispute with a Mr. Chaplin ("this morning both my horses are gone"); "I am somewhat loneson when I go to the house & miss you. I have wished several times this evening that I was at Rosedale; But it is useless for me to be seek for I know that I can not be with you for several days yet"
- Miscellaneous Brand Family Letters (selected) 1863, 1866-1867 & 1873
  - Moseley family letters [these are a four-page photocopy] 1863 Nov. 11
    W. W. Moseley, Gravel Hill, to "Dear Brother" [Dr. Charles Floyd Moseley, a Confederate surgeon], enclosing copy of letter of July 4, John W. Moseley, Gettysburg, to "Dear Mother" (Mrs. Charles Moseley) in which JWM describes himself as a mortally wounded prisoner of war and describes the battle and his wounding
  - Charles David Brand to William F. Brand 1866 Aug. 12
    "Will you said something about being an old grayheaded bachelor if you will come over on this side of the Ridge [Blue Ridge Mountains] where love & beauty reign I think you could find some old widdow that would sympathize with your in your troubles"; accuses him of badly treating Kate [Amanda C. Armentrout] and advises him not to marry her; describes "a grand memorial" held at the Buckingham Female Institute [1 August 1866] attended by 500 persons, "about two-thirds of that number lovely fair sex... I could hardly keep from falling in love with some of them"; mentions a recent visit to Scottsville; attached to this is a letter containing general news and comments from the Brand brothers' uncle C. F. Mosely [Charles Floyd Moseley?] to his nephew William
  - CDB, Marshall Place, to "Dear Brother" [WFB] 1866 Nov. 25
    says that if William becomes an old bachelor it is his fault because "you have treated Kate badly," advises him not to marry her "without love... I know she loves you more than any one else"; provides a short account his (CDB's) current courtship with a woman he refuses to identify by name; believes times are getting better, tobacco and oats crops are good but not wheat; urges WFB to visit their uncle during Christmas
  - Jane [Jane A. Brand?], Zephyrus [Hill?; state unknown], to "Dear Brother" [WFB] w/envelope addressed to Kate Armentrout, Greenville, Augusta County, Virginia 1867 Nov. 2
    : general family news; does not want to return to Virginia; encloses letter to "Dear Sister," [sister- in-law?] same date and place, misses friends and family in Virginia, appreciates offer to live with her brother William and Kate
  - Alice M ?, Marshall Place, to "Dear Cousin William" [WFB] 1873 July 16
    death of her grandmother last month and description of her final days; family news, crops are good, especially tobacco
- Miscellaneous Materials and Genealogical Notes ca. 1925, 1932 & 1959, n.d.
  - Note recorded in minutes of Tinkling Spring Church commemorating the life of its senior elder W. F. Brand who died 28 May 1932 1932 May
  - Newspaper article, "Letters from Civil War Soldier Describe His Life As Member of Confederate Army" News-Virginian (Waynesboro), page 4 1959 Dec. 5
    [includes photograph of William Francis Brand and Amanda Catherine Armentrout Brand]
  - "Col. Denison's Notes" 1959
    Photocopies of abbreviated typescripts and notes of selected Brand letters by Colonel S. L. Denison, chairman, Waynesboro Civil War Centennial Committee, 24 pp.
  - Poem addressed to "Miss A. C. Armentrout/At Home" n.d.
    Day, twenty-sixth of last May/Received from you without delay.. .," signed "A Friend"
  - n.d.
    "If anyone wants more information on the family of William Francis Brand and Amanda Catherine Brand.. ., " 2 pp.
  - "Family Record (Grandparent, Parents, Children)," 2 pp. n.d.